Johannes Correa

Career Summary

Johannes is a 18-years experienced Software Engineer with a broad experience in projects based on Java related technologies (JSP, JSF, Spring, JPA, among others) and methodologies like RUP and Scrum. He has evolved from Developer to Solutions Architect, leading teams of up to 20 people and participated in several training courses as facilitator to help the team improve their work.

Summary of Qualifications

Proficient In:

- Java
- 1PA
- Spring framework
- Spring boot
- Microservices
- Websphere
- Apache Tomcat
- Continuous Integration (Jenkins and Sonar)
- ATDD with Jbehave/Cucumber
- **TDD**

Languages

- Spanish (native speaker)
- English (Upper Intermmediate)

- **Unit Testing**
- Mocking
- Subversion
- Git
- MySQL/Maria DB
- Oracle
- **Application Profiling**
- JMeter for Load and
- Performance Testing

Career History

Blankfactor, Colombia

Java Practice Lead

Since April 2021.

Team lead for a project for a world-wide leading financial institution where we are maintaining and migrating a mobile app with native interfaces (Android and iOS) from a Ruby-based middletier to a Java-based middletier using technologies such Spring Boot, Spring Data JPA, Postgres and participating in the migration from AWS to Azure. As team lead I participate actively in development of features and fixes but also I am involved in the communication and relationship with the customer leaders and team members and management and tracking of the activities for our internal team.

Universidad Autónoma de Bucaramanga.

Specialization Teacher

During 4 years I have had the opportunity to participate as a Teacher in the course Advanced Topics in Software Development (32 hours). This course has been focused on Agile Software Development, specifically oriented to provide the students with the foundations to work with methodologies and tools like TDD, Continuous Integration and Delivery, Pair Programming, all of them worked alongside with a practical exercise that simulates a development team using Scrum.

Globant, Medellín, Colombia

Technical Lead

As Technical Lead for ThunderPod in the Crew Planning project, Johannes led technically a team of almost 20 members working in the migration of a Swing based application to a new web-based architecture. The new application was based on Spring technologies and used a mix of relational and non-relational storages to improve the usability and performance of the existing application. Johannes' role was mainly a technical and communication bridge between the Technical Leads from the client, who provided the architectural guidelines, and the team, in charge of implementing the application following those details.

From 2017-2019, 2021.

Oct. 2015-April 2021

- As Technical Lead for Danube Pod, into the Revenue Management area of Southwest Airlines, we participated in the implementation of new functionalities related to the processing of ATPCO files and some database views to summarize information for the FMDB system. As leader, Johannes helped the team to improve the usage of Sonar as a tool to track code quality and also helped in the reduction of the technical debt by proposing a strategy to implement some unit tests for the code implemented.
- From June/2017 to April/2001, Johannes was the technical leader for a team of up to 9 members working for the Parks and Resorts area of Disney in a migration project of a monolith to a microservices oriented architecture. The project is implemented using a set of technologies like Spring Boot, Spring, Retrofit, RxJava, DynamDB, Rabbit MQ, end-to-end functional testing by using the test tooling support offered by Spring and MockWebServer to mock the dependencies on other rest and soap services. On this project, the technical leaders on all the teams participate as active members of development activities, participating in the implementation and review of them.
 - o As part of the technical leadership, Johannes is responsible for guiding his colleagues in
 - their process of growth as part of their career path. This has been pursued by having constant 1:1 meetings where improving objectives are set and followed up.
- From June 2018 and until leaving the company, Johannes also participated as Technical Interviewer to help the company in the recruiting processes of new candidates and mentoring new Technical Interviewers.

INTERGRUPO, Medellín, Colombia

Dec. 2013 - Oct. 2015

Solutions Architect

- As part of the Innovation Office, Johannes was involved in research of new technologies, methodologies and tools to be introduced in the development process of the company. Main focus over the year 2014 was the adoption of PaaS based technologies that could be used to improve productivity into projects. Also he worked closely with Commercial Teams to improve the offering and project estimations based on such PaaS technologies.
- Additionally, Johannes was involved in some improvement activities focused on how the
 development teams were doing their work. Those activities focused on helping teams adopt
 agile technical practices such as TDD, BDD, Continuous Integration and Delivery, among others.

CEIBA SOFTWARE, Medellín, Colombia

Aug. 2012 - Nov. 2013

Solutions Architect

- As a team member of the Technical Office, Johannes led an internal project aimed at defining and implementing strategies for incorporating technical practices from TDD and BDD in the projects undertaken by the company. It also included improving some of the continuous integration practices that were already in place and helping teams to identify aspects to improve in projects in order to reduce technical debt.
- Team Leader for the design and development of a mobile-enabled web application, using GWT as
 the main web technology, to enable the salesforce of the customer to provide price projections of
 insurance products to actual and potential customers and, with those projections, initiate the
 expedition of new insurance policies.

INTERGRUPO, Medellín, Colombia

Apr. 2010 - Sept. 2010

Applications/Enterprise Architect

For 6 months, Johannes was assigned as staff insource to the Enterprise Applications Architecture
area of Bancolombia, the larkest bank in Colombia, being involved in several projects with the
primary role of verifying that development or acquisition projects were aligned with the
architecture's guidelines and strategy of Bancolombia, validation of implementation designs and
analysis of best practices.

Software Developer/Software Architect

May. 2005 – Apr. 2010

 Johannes worked mainly with the Electronic Channels area from Bancolombia, developing new features for the different applications they have, which provide transactional functionalities to the customers of the bank. His main accomplishments achieved during this period were:

- Johannes led the implementation of a framework, known as FWTX, to reduce the time required to implement new transactions for some of the electronic channels of the bank. The framework aimed to provide an infrastructure to implement transactions and acts as a broker between client applications and the transactional backend that run in an AS400 platform. This framework allowed development teams to reduce the time of implementation between 30-40%.
- Johannes led several projects and teams in charge of implementing new transactions using the FTWX and features and extensions to FWTX itself. At the peak moment, Johannes was leading up to 4 teams simultaneously, each of them with up to 4 members.
- Johannes led the implementation of secure Web Services for several projects following WS-Security specification, using header signature and body encryption to allow those applications to integrate with other middleware applications and even with the transactional channels.

FACTORING MARKET, Medellín, Colombia

Apr. 2003 - May. 2005

Software Developer

- Johannes was involved as Software Developer in the analysis, design, implementation and testing
 of new features for the electronic factoring platform that the company had already implemented.
- Johannes proposed and implemented a redesign of the messaging notification feature to the platform users by using lightweight templates, replacing a heavy implementation based on XML marshalling and unmarshalling.
- Johannes led the design and implementation of a collaborative tool with chat, forums and mail notifications for internal use of one of the Investors of the company.

PRAGMA, Medellín, Colombia

Mar. 2002 – Mar. 2003

Software Developer

- Johannes implemented algorithms based on numerical methods to calculate projections about pension value for users of one of the largest Retirement Funds of the country.
- Johannes was involved in the maintenance and implementation of new features for several tools already implemented for the same Fund mentioned above.

Education

Eafit University, Medellín, Colombia BS, Systems Engineering

Jan. 1997 – Dec. 2002

Carlos III University, Madrid, Spain Msc, Computer Science

Sept. 2010 - Jul. 2012